<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1"?>

<document>

  <properties>
    <title>Trouble Shooting HttpClient</title>
    <author email="adrian@ephox.com">Adrian Sutton</author>
    <revision>$Id: troubleshooting.xml 155418 2005-02-26 13:01:52Z dirkv $</revision>
  </properties>

  <body>

    <section name="Introduction">
      <p>This document outlines some of the techniques that often help when
        trying to track down a problem in <em>HttpClient</em>.  Please try the suggestions
        on this page before emailing the user or dev lists with questions.  If
        none of these things help, please provide the information they provide to
        help the developers track down the problem.</p>
    </section>

    <section name="Things To Try">
      <ol>
        <li>Try connecting with a normal browser and make sure the server gives
        the right response.</li>
        
        <li>If you're using a proxy server try without it if possible.</li>

        <li>Try the same code on a different server (preferably running
        different server software).</li>

        <li>Check that your code matches the general pattern for using
          <em>HttpClient</em> as described in the <a
        href="tutorial.html">tutorial</a>.</li>

        <li>Set the <a href="logging.html">logging level</a> to debug and check
        the output for the cause of the problem.</li>

        <li>Enable the <a href="logging.html">wire trace</a> and follow the
        communication between the client and server to determine where the
        problem is occurring.</li>

        <li>Use telnet or netcat to manually send the request to the server.
        This is particularly useful once you think you know what the problem is
        and you want to easily test that changing what <em>HttpClient</em> sends will
        fix it.</li>

        <li>Use netcat in listen mode to act as the server and check how
          <em>HttpClient</em> handles various responses.</li>

        <li>Try updating to the latest nightly build of <em>HttpClient</em>.  Bugs
        happen and they are generally fixed pretty quickly so testing against
        the latest build is often worthwhile.</li>
      </ol>
    </section>

    <section name="Asking For Help">
      <p>If you've tried the things above and still can't work out how to fix
      the problem, it might be time to contact the <a
      href="mail-lists.html">mailing list</a> for support.  All questions, bug
      reports etc should be directed to the HttpClient development list as all
      the really knowledgeable people for HttpClient are there and most are not
      also on the commons-user list.</p>

      <p>When you do send off the email, please include as much detail as you
      can, particularly including attaching wire trace logs as there is almost
      nothing we can do to help without them.
      If you are seeing exceptions being thrown the full stack
      trace is essential to tracking down the problem.  Any of the information
      you gained from the "things to try" section above are probably worth
      mentioning.</p>
    </section>

    <section name="Reporting Bugs">
      <p>If you're fairly certain that the problem is a bug in <em>HttpClient</em> or
        something that <em>HttpClient</em> doesn't currently support but probably should,
      log it in <a href="http://issues.apache.org/bugzilla/">Bugzilla</a>.
      Make sure you spend some time searching the existing bugs to make sure it
      hasn't already been logged.  If you're unsure about whether or not to log
      something in Bugzilla, it's probably worth bringing it up on the
      developer mailing list to clarify the situation.</p>
    </section>
  </body>
</document>
