<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1"?>

<document>

  <properties>
    <title>Status</title>
    <author email="commons-dev@jakarta.apache.org">Commons Documentation Team</author>
    <author email="remy@apache.org">Remy Maucherat</author>
    <author email="rwaldhoff@apache.org">Rodney Waldhoff</author>
    <author email="jsdever@apache.org">Jeff Dever</author>
    <revision>$Id: status.xml 134503 2004-01-17 05:43:14Z  $</revision>
  </properties>

  <body>

    <section name="Current Status">    	
        <p>The HttpClient development team is pleased to announce the third release candidate 
        of <em>HttpClient 2.0</em>. We are confident that <em>HttpClient 2.0</em> has reached 
        the required level of maturity, and we hope to have a final 2.0 release soon.</p>

	<p>Only critical or major bug fixes and javadocs enhancements will be made to the 2.0 
        code base before the final release.</p>

	<p>Meanwhile, the HttpClient development team has been busy working toward a post 2.0
	release. The next version of <em>HttpClient</em> is going to build upon the 
        foundation laid with <em>HttpClient 2.0</em> while addressing those architectural 
        shortcomings and flaws identified in the course of 2.0 development. Several well known 
        and much complained about problems cannot be resolved while maintaining complete 2.0 API 
        compatibility. The primary objective of the next version is to fix those design limitations, 
        breaking 2.0 API compatibility where absolutely unavoidable, while preserving overall 
        compatibility with 2.0 use patterns.</p>

       <p>We already have a new preference architecture in place that will help us provide a
        fine-grained control over HttpClient without polluting its API with too many options. We 
        have also completely reworked redirect/authentication/retry logic and can now support 
        cross-host redirects, a much complained about limitation of <em>HttpClient 2.0</em>.</p>

       <p>Depending upon how drastic those API changes are going to be, the next version of 
         HttpClient will be designated as <tt>2.1</tt>, <tt>2.5</tt> or <tt>3.0</tt>.
         The decision will be made prior to the 2.0 final release.</p>

	<p>It is important to note that HttpClient CVS HEAD is no longer fully compatible 
	 with 2.0 APIs. We strongly encourage using the <tt>HTTPCLIENT_2_0_BRANCH</tt>
         until the next version's APIs are stabilized.</p>
    </section>

    <section name="Release Info">
      <p>Current Release: <a href="http://jakarta.apache.org/builds/jakarta-commons/release/commons-httpclient/v2.0/">
          Release 2.0 Release Candidate 3</a></p>
      <p>Planned Next Release: 2.0 Final</p>
    </section>

  </body>

</document>
