<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1"?>

<document>

  <properties>
    <title>HttpClient Applications</title>
    <author email="commons-dev@jakarta.apache.org">Commons Documentation Team</author>
    <author email="rwaldhoff@apache.org">Rodney Waldhoff</author>
    <author email="jsdever@apache.org">Jeff Dever</author>
    <revision>$Id: applications.xml 134090 2003-02-09 16:17:34Z jsdever $</revision>
  </properties>

  <body>

    <section name="HttpClient Powered">
      <p>
        The following projects and applications use <em>HttpClient</em>.
      </p>

      <dl>

        <dt><a href="http://jakarta.apache.org/slide/">Jakarta Slide</a></dt>
        <dd>
          Jakarta Slide is an open-source project composed of multiple modules tied
          together using WebDAV. It includes a CM API, a WebDAV server, WebDAV client
          APIs, J2EE compliant stores and more.
        </dd>

        <dt><a href="http://jakarta.apache.org/commons/latka/">Jakarta Commons Latka</a></dt>
        <dd>
          Latka is a functional (end-to-end) testing tool. It is implemented in Java, and uses an XML syntax 
          to define a series of HTTP (or HTTPS) requests and a set of validations used to verify that the 
          request was processed correctly.
        </dd>

        <dt><a href="http://www.nortelnetworks.com/">Nortel Networks</a></dt>
        <dd>
          Operator Simulation Tool (OST) - A server side performance and scalability testing tool
          uses HttpClient to drive loads to web based server applications.
        </dd>

        <dt><a href="http://htmlunit.sourceforge.net/">HtmlUnit</a></dt>
        <dd>
          HtmlUnit is a java unit testing framework for testing web based applications.
          HtmlUnit models the returned document so that you deal with pages and forms and tables. 
        </dd>

        <dt><a href="http://jakarta.apache.org/cactus/">Jakarta Cactus</a></dt>
        <dd>
           Cactus is a simple test framework for unit testing server-side java code.
           The intent of Cactus is to lower the cost of writing tests for server-side code.
        </dd>

        <dt><a href="http://www.jcp.org/en/jsr/detail?id=147">JSR147</a></dt>
        <dd>
          Workspace Versioning and Configuration Management.
          (implementation not finalized but considering Slide and HttpClient)
        </dd>

        <dt><a href="http://www.nose.ch/">NOSE Applied Intelligence ag</a></dt>
        <dd>
          HttpClient is used in a number of applications:
          <ol>
            <li>ACE: A groupware (fat client) and document management system for closed user groups for project management, e-learning etc. HttpClient is used for communication between the user client and server to transfer XML messages.</li>
            <li>Desktop Navigator: Company wide, centrally managed "bookmark list" that integrates in the Desktop. HttpClient is used to check links.</li>
            <li>Backend of a Webapp for a major swiss airline. HttpClient gets XML data from the business layer.</li>
          </ol>
        </dd>
        
        <dt><a href="http://www.designacourse.com/">MindIQ's Design-a-Course</a></dt>
        <dd>
          Design-a-Course, a quick, easy, and inexpensive e-learning software tool allows novice users to 
          create sophisticated web-based training (WBT) courses within minutes.
        </dd>
        
        <dt><a href="http://www.contactoffice.com/">ContactOffice</a></dt>
        <dd>
            ContactOffice is a complete groupware solution ('Virtual office') combining mail, 
            calendar, storage, contacts, and more.  HttpClient is used for back-end tasks
            such as inter-server communication and SMS transmission.
        </dd>

      </dl>

      <hr width="50%"/>
      <p>
        To have your application listed, write to
        <a href="mailto:commons-httpclient-dev@jakarta.apache.org?subject=HttpClient%20Powered">
          commons-httpclient-dev@jakarta.apache.org</a>.
      </p>
    </section>

  </body>

</document>
