<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1"?>

<document>

  <properties>
    <title>HttpClient Applications</title>
    <author email="commons-dev@jakarta.apache.org">Commons Documentation Team</author>
    <author email="rwaldhoff@apache.org">Rodney Waldhoff</author>
    <author email="jsdever@apache.org">Jeff Dever</author>
    <revision>$Id: applications.xml 134566 2004-04-19 19:33:21Z olegk $</revision>
  </properties>

  <body>

    <section name="HttpClient Powered">
      <p>
        The following projects and applications use <em>HttpClient</em>.
      </p>

      <dl>

        <dt><a href="http://jakarta.apache.org/slide/">Jakarta Slide</a></dt>
        <dd>
          Jakarta Slide is an open-source project composed of multiple modules tied
          together using WebDAV. It includes a CM API, a WebDAV server, WebDAV client
          APIs, J2EE compliant stores and more.
        </dd>

        <dt><a href="http://www.jcp.org/en/jsr/detail?id=147">JSR 147</a></dt>
        <dd>
          Workspace Versioning and Configuration Management.
          Software AG is going to implement the current draft of JSR 147 API.
          The implementation will be based on the Jakarta Commons HttpClient
          and located in the Jakarta Slide project.
        </dd>

        <dt><a href="http://jakarta.apache.org/commons/latka/">Jakarta Commons Latka</a></dt>
        <dd>
          Latka is a functional (end-to-end) testing tool. It is implemented in Java, 
          and uses an XML syntax to define a series of HTTP (or HTTPS) requests and a 
          set of validations used to verify that the request was processed correctly.
        </dd>

        <dt><a href="http://jakarta.apache.org/cactus/">Jakarta Cactus</a></dt>
        <dd>
           Cactus is a simple test framework for unit testing server-side java code.
           The intent of Cactus is to lower the cost of writing tests for server-side code.
        </dd>

        <dt><a href="http://htmlunit.sourceforge.net/">HtmlUnit</a></dt>
        <dd>
          HtmlUnit is a java unit testing framework for testing web based applications.
          HtmlUnit models the returned document so that you deal with pages and forms and tables. 
        </dd>

        <dt><a href="http://xins.sourceforge.net/">The XINS/Java Client Framework</a></dt>
        <dd>
          XINS is a framework for describing and implementing API's that can be accessed 
          by browsers. In contrast to SOAP and XML-RPC, HTML-based test forms can be generated
          to make calls to the API
        </dd>

        <dt><a href="http://www.limewire.org/">LimeWire</a></dt>
        <dd>
          LimeWire is a robust, open-source, multi-platform, consumer-oriented P2P file-sharing 
          client.  LimeWire uses HttpClient because it is a highly customizable and efficient
          HTTP manager, and has proven itself to work without any hitches on the hundreds of 
          thousands of daily users of LimeWire
        </dd>

        <dt><a href="http://www.nortelnetworks.com/">Nortel Networks</a></dt>
        <dd>
          Operator Simulation Tool (OST) - A server side performance and scalability testing tool
          uses HttpClient to drive loads to web based server applications.
        </dd>

        <dt><a href="http://www.nose.ch/">NOSE Applied Intelligence ag</a></dt>
        <dd>
          HttpClient is used in a number of applications:
          <ol>
            <li>ACE: A groupware (fat client) and document management system for closed user groups 
               for project management, e-learning etc. HttpClient is used for communication between 
               the user client and server to transfer XML messages.</li>
            <li>Desktop Navigator: Company wide, centrally managed "bookmark list" that integrates in 
               the Desktop. HttpClient is used to check links.</li>
            <li>Backend of a Webapp for a major swiss airline. HttpClient gets XML data from the 
               business layer.</li>
          </ol>
        </dd>
        
        <dt><a href="http://www.mindiq.com/elearning/dac/index.php">MindIQ's Design-a-Course</a></dt>
        <dd>
          Design-a-Course, a quick, easy, and inexpensive e-learning software tool allows 
          novice users to create sophisticated web-based training (WBT) courses within minutes.
        </dd>

        <dt><a href="http://www3.contactoffice.com/">ContactOffice</a></dt>
        <dd>
          ContactOffice is a complete groupware solution ('Virtual office') combining mail, 
          calendar, storage, contacts, and more.  HttpClient is used for back-end tasks
          such as inter-server communication and SMS transmission.
        </dd>
        
        <dt><a href="http://www.newknow.com/">Newknow</a></dt>
        <dd>
          Newknow is a Knowledge Management Suite based on Artificial Intelligence, 
          Collaboration and Document Management and we use Commons HttpClient as part 
          of our Knowledge Spider.  This Spider retrieves all the information gathered 
          by the Agents and the corporative sources on the network.
        </dd>

        <dt><a href="http://www.xam.de/dev/de4d2c/">Web Abstraction Layer (WAL)</a></dt>
        <dd>
          Web Abstraction Layer (formerly known as de4d2c) - development environment 4 
          documents 2 content - is an in-browser web page wrapper development system 
          that returns it's extraction result as XML using XSLT generated from intuitive 
          user input. Commons HttpClient is used as the robust base of the whole system.
        </dd>

	<dt><a href="http://www.reflexe.fr/html/ultraseek.html">Term Highlighting for Verity 
          Ultraseek search results</a></dt>
	<dd>
	 Reflexe Technologies has developed a servlet-based application that works 
	 with Verity Ultraseek, formerly known as Inktomi
	 Enterprise Search, that highlights terms that match search query, by
	 intercepting HTTP communication between the browser and the original
	 document server.  It can highlight terms in HTML documents, as well as Word,
	 Excel, Powerpoint, and Acrobat PDF documents, and uses the Jakarta
	 HttpClient for better performance than that provided by the standard J2SE
	 platform, and in particular because it must be able to offer NTLM
	 authentification when required.
	</dd>

	<dt><a href="http://www.muleumo.org/">Mule - Universal Message Objects</a></dt>
        <dd>
         Mule is a robust and highly scalable broker and services ESB framework. It
         is designed as a light-weight, event-driven component technology that
         handles communication with disparate systems transparently providing a
         simple component interface.
	</dd>

      </dl>

      <hr width="50%"/>
      <p>
        To have your application listed, write to
        <a href="mailto:commons-httpclient-dev@jakarta.apache.org?subject=HttpClient%20Powered">
          commons-httpclient-dev@jakarta.apache.org</a>.
      </p>
    </section>

  </body>

</document>
